Yes, migration and immigration is kind
of like a repeated chorus in the song of
US history and baby it's time to sing
that thing one last time in the present
time period. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked then raise your
glasses and let's get to it. Okay, so
hopefully you'll remember from unit
eight that I told you about the Sunbelt
migration in which millions of Americans
moved from the Northeast and Midwest
states into the Southern and Western
states. And here's where I tell you that
this trend just went right ahead and
continued after 1980 and led to
significant political, economic, and
cultural consequences. And if you want
to know what those consequences were
then don't worry because I'm about to
I'm explaining it up real nice for you.
So, first of all, the Sunbelt migration
had significant political effects. Now,
because political representation in the
House of Representatives is based on
population, this migration led to a
significant transfer of political power
toward the Sunbelt states as their
populations grew bigger. For example, in
1980 Georgia had 12 electoral votes,
Texas had 26, and California had 45. And
all these are Sunbelt states. But by
2020 Georgia had 16, Texas had 38, and
California had 55. By contrast, in 1980
Michigan, which is one of the states
that those Sunbelt migrants were moving
away from, had 21 electoral votes and by
2020 they had 16. Moment of silence for
Michigan. Okay, that's enough. You see,
Michigan is part of what became known as
the Rust Belt, which refers to a cluster
of northern states that previously
wielded enormous economic power because
of its manufacturing industry. However,
as a result of the outsourcing of
manufacturing to other nations, the
region's industrial infrastructure has
become rusted and become a symbol of
both a globalized economy and the mass
migration of Americans into Sunbelt
states. And I'd tell you more about it,
but I'm a little rusty on the details.
Anyway, second, the Sunbelt migration
after 1980 had significant economic
effects as well. So, hopefully you'll
remember that one of the big reasons
Americans started migrating their hind
parts en masse to the Sunbelt was
because of the lure of finding jobs,
especially in the defense industry
during the Cold War. But as more and
more Americans moved to those states,
significant economic effects started
popping up as well. For example, the
rise of Silicon Valley in Northern
California has become a powerful
contribution both to the domestic
American economy as well as the global
economy. Like this area has in many ways
become one of the high-tech capitals of
the world and as such is home to
enormous companies like Apple and
Google, Nvidia, and many others. And for
the most part, the tech products sold by
these companies are not actually made in
Silicon Valley. No, it's a globalized
economy, so their phones and computers
and microchips are made by foreign
manufacturing sites. However, because
these companies are located in this
area, it creates a high demand for
well-educated, highly skilled knowledge
workers and that led to the
establishment and growth of some of
America's most prestigious universities
like Stanford University and University
of California, Berkeley. Additionally,
the Sunbelt migration has boosted the
economic contribution of the oil and
energy industries in Texas, as well as a
rise in manufacturing and service jobs
in Southern states. And finally, let me
tell you about the cultural effects of
the Sunbelt migration that occurred
because of the greater diversity that
came with the growth of urban centers
like Atlanta and Austin and Miami and
the like. And the one cultural effect
that I'll focus on here is the growth
and influence of Southern hip hop during
this period. Now, in case you didn't
know, hip hop originated as a new
musical style in the late 1970s and
early 80s in New York City. However, as
a result of the growing influence of the
South, Jermaine Dupri founded So So Def
Records in 1993, which became the first
major hip hop label formed out of
Atlanta, Georgia. And as a result of
massive hits from artists like Kris
Kross and Xscape, the Southern flavor of
hip hop became a significant influence
on the genre across the country. And
look, as much as I know that everyone on
the internet wants a middle-aged bald
man to keep whitesplaining hip hop to
them, I think I'm going to shift to
something I have a little more authority
talking about and that's the APUSH
National Exam. That nasty assessment is
coming up quick, fast, and in a hurry.
And if you need help studying as fast as
possible for it, then you might want to
check out my APUSH Heimler Review Guide.
It is, as the hip hoppers would say,
dope. So sorry, I will stop now. Link in
the description. Okay, so not only were
Americans themselves migrating in large
numbers after 1980, but international
immigration spiked as well. And this
increase was largely the effect of the
Great Society era Immigration Act of
1965, which repealed discriminatory
immigration quotas put in place during
the 1920s. So, after 1980 the majority
of immigrants that came to the United
States arrived from various Latin
American countries, as well as South and
East Asia. And that was much different
compared to previous immigration spikes
we've considered in this course, where
the majority of folks coming in were
European. Anyway, by the year 2000
Latino immigrants had become the largest
minority in the United States, a
position previously held by black
Americans. And then Asians of various
stripes made up about a third of all
immigrants in the 1990s and early 2000s.
And not only did many of these
immigrants fill essential low-wage jobs
that contributed greatly to the domestic
economy, many of these workers also sent
money home to their families in the form
of remittances, which simultaneously led
to significant global economic growth.
Now, just like other waves of
immigration in US history, this
post-1980 wave provoked debates about
the place of immigrants in American
society. And in light of so many
foreign-born people entering the
population, one particularly heated
debate centered around exactly what
constituted American identity. And I
hope that sounds familiar because the
very same debate erupted during every
other wave of immigration we've
considered. Now, some Americans invoked
the old melting pot imagery, insisting
that there was only one way to be an
American and that as immigrants
consented to having their own cultural
distinctiveness melted away, they would
emerge as citizens that were culturally
indistinguishable from native-born
Americans. However, other Americans
argued that assimilation was an attack
on immigrant culture and instead argued
for the embrace of multiculturalism.
idea here was that the American
identity, by its very nature, was not a
single identity, but rather made up of
many different identities held together
by a commitment to the ideals of
democracy and freedom and other common
American values. And so, that was the
debate in general, but now let me give
you two specific developments that
illustrate the conflict. First of all,
the debate around American identity
stirred up some heat with the growing
implementation of English as a second
language programs in public schools. The
idea was that students for whom English
was not their first language would be
taught in their native tongue until they
could acquire a working knowledge of
English and this would be a scaffolded
program over time. argued that such
programs would prevent immigrant
students from falling behind since they
wouldn't have to add the additional
burden of learning English to the
burdens of learning math and science and
all the rest. But detractors argued that
such programs delayed students' ability
to learn English and hindered the speed
at which they could assimilate into
American society. In other words, this
side argued that despite the fact that
the United States has never officially
designated English as its official
language, to be an American you damn
well better speak American. Anyway,
researchers have continued to study ESL
education and the results have been
somewhat inconclusive and have remained
hotly debated even to this day. And then
the second example of the debate around
American identity is the model minority
stereotype. So, the growing number of
Asian American immigrants led to the
generalization and stereotyping of their
community, but it was a different kind
of stereotyping than we've considered
before. For example, back in the Gilded
Age the prevailing stereotype of Chinese
immigrants is that they were
disease-ridden and always plotting to
steal jobs from white workers. And just
in case it isn't clear, that would be an
example of a stereotype that's uh
negative. But starting in the 1960s,
Asian Americans were often stereotyped
as the model minority in the United
States because they worked hard and
averaged higher scores on standardized
tests than other groups. Additionally,
the model minority stereotype praised
Asian Americans' seemingly natural
tendency for obedience on account of
their Confucian morals. And if you're
like, that kind of sounds like a
compliment, then you've probably never
been on the receiving end of such a
stereotype. First of all, the model
minority status was applied to them as a
way to criticize other minorities,
especially black Americans, for the
cultural upheaval caused during the
Civil Rights Movement. In other words,
those black agitators who were messing
everything up just to get their freedom
were considered the worst kind of
minority. And so, the implicit message
was, why can't you guys just be quiet
and work hard like those Asian
Americans? And then second, some Asian
Americans claim that the stereotype was
harmful because it put unrealistic
expectations upon them to succeed at a
higher rate than other Americans. And
third, the stereotype provided a means
by which other Americans could dismiss
hard work Asian Americans put in. For
example, if an Asian American student
scored well on an exam, then other
students might just attribute that to
his ethnicity instead of acknowledging
the enormous effort required to earn
such a score. Anyway, these stereotypes
and debates about immigration continue
up to this present moment. And if
history is any indicator, we're going to
keep debating those issues for a long
time to come. Well, okay, you can click
here to watch my other unit nine videos
or you can click here to grab my APUSH
Heimler Review Guide, which has
everything you need to help you get a
five on your exam in May. I'm glad you
came around and I'll catch on the flip
flop. Heimler out.